And continuing on our strategy to solve commercial problems with LMS, we get to step four, which is
LMS로 상업적 문제를 해결하는 전략을 계속하겠습니다 4단계를 거치죠 모델
about optimizing our model to solve problems really, really well.
최적화하기입니다 문제를 아주 잘 해결하기 위해서요
Taking it beyond the pre-trained model that we might have, um, either or an existing frontier model
기존의 선구 모델이나 훈련된 모델을 넘어서서 더 많은
and getting more juice out of it.
걸 끌어내는 거죠
So there are these three different approaches that two of them we've used, and one of them talked about
세 가지 다른 접근법이 있는데 두 가지는 이미 사용했고 한 가지는 많이
there is prompting that we've used a ton now, which is things like multi-shot prompting, chaining
사용했다는 프롬프트입니다 멀티샷 프롬프트, 여러 프롬프트가 있을 때 연결하기,
when we have multiple prompts and using tools.
도구를 사용하는 것 등이죠
These are all ways to get better outcomes.
모두 더 나은 결과를 얻는 방법이죠. Get up!
There is Rag, of course, that you're now super familiar with.
여러분이 아주 잘 아는 랙도 있어요
I do hope you've built that extra project to be doing a knowledge work on on your own life.
자신의 삶을 위한 지식을 쌓을 수 있는 프로젝트를 만들었길 바라요
Uh, so there is rag and then the new thing, Fine tuning, which is about training the model to be
래그와 새로운 게 있어요 파인 튜닝인데 모델이 더 나아지도록 훈련하는
even better.
거예요
So these these are the three techniques.
이 세 가지 기술이 필요해요
And there's certainly a lot of confusion out there.
확실히 혼란스러운 상황이에요
There's a lot of questions I get asked about.
Get in get 질문이 많아요
How do you decide which technique to use in which situation.
어떤 기술을 어떤 상황에서 쓸지 어떻게 결정하나요?
And of course, it's possible to use all the techniques together, but one does typically, uh, focus
물론 모든 기술을 함께 사용할 수도 있지만 보통은 한 가지 기술에 집중하죠
on one, uh, at least initially.
적어도 처음에는요
And it's worth pointing out that the first two techniques there are inference time techniques.
첫 두 가지 기술은 시간을 추론하는 기술이에요
These are about taking a trained model and at inference time, figuring out how to get more juice out
숙련된 모델을 취하고 추론 시간에 어떻게 즙을 더 얻을 수 있는지 알아내는 과정이죠.
of it.
세 번째는 훈련 시간과 기술이에요
It's about saying, all right, let's take a pre-trained model and figure out how to supply more data,
미리 훈련된 모델을 가지고 더 많은 데이터를 공급하고
to tweak the weights to make it even better at solving its problem.
무게를 조정해서 문제를 더 잘 해결하자는 거죠
So to talk about the benefits of each of those techniques just very quickly in prompting, obviously
각각의 테크닉의 장점에 대해 아주 빠르게 말씀드릴게요 물론
it's super fast to do this.
아주 빠르죠
We've done this so quickly, so easily having different prompting strategies, uh, with maybe the exception
아주 빠르고 쉽게 다양한 프롬프트 전략을 쓸 수 있죠 도구는 예외지만 비트만 좀 더 복잡해요
of tools, was a little bit more involved, but still, you get the idea.
그래도 감은 잡으셨죠
You can just replicate that.
그걸 복제하면 돼요
You can quite easily get to a point where you are continually improving, uh, the prompt messages to
쉽게 개선되는 지점에 도달할 수 있어요 신속하게 LLM에 메시지를 보내면서 점점 더 나은
an LLM and getting better and better results.
결과를 내는 거죠 Get it
And you typically see very quick direct improvement from it.
일반적으로 아주 빠른 직접적 향상을 볼 수 있죠
You add in some multi-shot, uh, prompt, uh, background, some context into your prompts, and you
멀티샷 프롬프트 배경, 컨텍스트를 프롬프트 안에 추가하면 즉시 개선되죠
immediately get the improvement.
Get up
And it's a low cost too.
비용도 저렴하고요
So lots of benefits of using prompting.
즉, 입력을 하면 장점이 많아요
So rag, uh, has the benefit of bringing about this, this strong accuracy because you can pluck out,
랙은 매우 정확하게 정보를 수집할 수 있습니다 LLM을 무장할
uh, this, uh, this very specific fact of information to arm the LLM with.
수 있는 아주 구체적인 정보를 캐낼 수 있죠
It's, it's very scalable in that you can have huge quantities of data that can pour in, and your Rag
매우 확장 가능합니다 엄청난 양의 데이터가 쏟아져 들어올 수 있고 래그 파이프라인이 관련 컨텍스트를
pipeline can pluck out the relevant context, so you don't have to spend all the extra money pumping
제거할 수 있으니까요 모델에 점점 더 큰 프롬프트를 만드는 데 추가
bigger and bigger prompts to your model.
돈을 쓰지 않아도 되죠
And that ties to the third point, which is that it's efficient because you can you can do that.
세 번째 요점과 연결됩니다 효율적이라는 거죠 그렇게 할 수 있으니까요
Um, so fine tuning.
미세한 조율이죠
So what are the benefits?
어떤 혜택이 있죠?
So it allows you to build deep expertise, specialist skill sets into your model.
깊은 전문 지식과 전문 기술을 모델에 구축할 수 있게 해주죠
You can build a model that is really great at doing something in a way that is very nuanced.
아주 미묘한 방식으로 뭔가를 하는 데 뛰어난 모델을 만들 수 있어요
So it's not just being given an extra fact.
추가적인 사실만 알려주는 게 아니에요
Um, about the CEO.
CEO 말인데요
What was our CEO's name?
대표 이름이 뭐였죠?
Avery Lancaster.
에이버리 랭커스터요
It's not just being given a specific fact about Avery and what she used to do.
에이버리가 과거에 뭘 했는지 구체적인 사실만 알려주는 게 아니에요
Uh, it's something which over time is learning.
시간이 지나면서 배우는 거예요
I don't know the careers of CEOs, or it's learning about the insurer Elm Company and more about its
CEO들의 경력은 몰라요 인큐러 엘름 컴퍼니와 그 문화와 통신에
culture and about its communications.
대해 배우는 거죠
So it gets this deeper insight, which allows it to show a kind of almost human like ability to reason
더 깊은 통찰력을 얻어서 보여주는 데이터를 추론하는 인간 같은
about the data that it's being showed.
능력을 보여줘요
So it's it's much more of a, um, it's, it's a much deeper way to change the abilities and capabilities
모델의 능력과 기능을 바꾸는 훨씬 심오한 방법이죠 시간
of the model than the inference time techniques.
추론 기술보다요
It allows a model to learn a different style and tone.
모델이 다른 스타일과 톤을 익히게 해주죠
Of course, you can achieve some of that by just prompting, as we saw early on when we just added a
물론 일부는 그냥 요청만 하면 할 수 있습니다 앞서 시스템 프롬프트를
system prompt and asked for for snarky comedic style, or when we had llms battling and we had a GPT
추가하고 비꼬는 코믹한 스타일을 요청했을 때나 llms 배틀이 있었을 때 GPT 40이 상대였다면요
So you can do that with with system prompts.
시스템 프롬프트와 함께 할 수 있어요
But if you want a very subtle tone, like you want a model that's going to emulate the the style of
하지만 고객 서비스 전문가들의 스타일을 모방하는 아주
your customer service specialists who've been trained over many years, then they need it will need
섬세한 톤의 모델을 원한다면 많은 데이터를 봐야겠죠
A lot of examples to learn from.
배울 점이 많아요
Um, and then the fourth point is that whilst this is something which requires a big investment in training,
네 번째 요점은 이 기능은 훈련에 많은 투자가 필요하지만 일단 훈련이 끝나면
once you've trained it, you can then run it at inference time.
추론 시간에 실행할 수 있다는 거예요
And you don't need to do things like in Rag.
랙 같은 건 필요 없어요
You have to then go and look up the context and provide that in the context that's no longer needed,
그러면 컨텍스트를 찾아서 더 이상 필요하지 않은 컨텍스트에서 제공해야 합니다
because you've already baked that into the model's weights.
왜냐하면 모델의 무게에 이미 굽어 놓았기 때문이죠
So it's faster.
더 빠르게요
So what about the cons?
단점은 뭐죠?
Well, many of these cons follow from the pros of the others, as you will see.
단점의 대부분은 장점을 따라가는 거죠
Uh, in the case of prompting, one con is that it's limited by the total context window.
어, 프롬프트할 때 단점 중 하나는 전체 컨텍스트 창에 의해 제한된다는 거예요
Of course, you can only shove so much in the prompt, and even if you do use up, even if you've got
물론 프롬프트에 밀어 넣는 것에는 한계가 있습니다. 다 사용한다고
mega context windows like Gemini one five flash, uh, the million tokens, if you remember that, um,
해도, 제미니1-5 플래시처럼 메가 컨텍스트 윈도우를 가지고 있고 백만
you still find that if you pump lots and lots into that context, then you get somewhat diminishing
토큰을 가지고 있다고 해도, 컨텍스트에 많은 양을 집어넣어도
Returns from how much it learns from that at inference times, and obviously.
결과물은 감소합니다. 추론 시간 동안 학습하는 양에 비해서요.
Inference itself becomes slower and more expensive.
추론 자체가 느려지고 비용이 더 들죠
The more context you are pumping in.
더 많은 맥락을 끌어당기죠
And if you're doing something like a prompt chaining when you're making multiple inference calls to
프롬프트 연결 같은 걸 작업하는 경우 큰 문제를 해결하기 위해 다수의
solve a bigger problem, then of course that slows everything down.
추론 호출을 할 경우 모든 게 느려지죠
So rag some of the cons it's more of a lift to build it.
단점을 없애고 짓는 게 더 어렵겠어요
Um, you need the vector database.
벡터 데이터베이스가 필요해요
You need to populate that vector database.
벡터 데이터베이스를 채워야 해요
Um, it needs the, uh, sort of the, it needs the knowledge base to be supplied and kept up to date,
그래서 필요한 게 최신 정보를 제공하고 유지해야 합니다 만약 에이버리 랭커스터가
presumably if it's giving accurate data, if Avery Lancaster steps down as CEO, will need to make sure
CEO 자리에서 물러난다면 누더기에도 정확한 데이터가 반영되어야
that the rag, uh, effect reflects that.
하겠죠
Um, and it lacks nuance.
뉘앙스가 부족해요
Um, it doesn't have the same, um, ability to to learn the deeper meaning behind the data.
데이터 뒤에 숨겨진 더 깊은 의미를 알아내는 능력이 없어요
It's just taking facts and the negatives of fine tuning.
섬세 조율의 사실과 단점을 취할 뿐이죠
Of course it is.
당연히 그렇겠죠
It's hard.
어렵네요
It's harder to to build it.
만들기가 더 어렵죠
It's going to be we're going to have a lot of fun with it, but it's going to be that we're going to
아주 재미있을 거예요 땀도 많이 나겠지만요
It's going to be difficult.
쉽지 않을 거예요
Um, you need a ton of data.
데이터가 엄청 많이 필요해요
You need a lot of examples.
예시가 많이 필요하죠
Uh, it's, uh, depends on on how specialized you want to be and your objectives.
어느 정도 전문화하고 싶은지 목표에 따라 달라요
But generally speaking, we'll see that there's going to be a high data need, and there's going to
일반적으로 보면 데이터 수요가 높을 것이고 훈련 비용이
be a training cost.
들 거예요
There's one more con that's that's often talked about, which is known as catastrophic forgetting,
자주 언급되는 단점이 하나 더 있어요 재앙적 망각이라고 하는데 아주
which sounds very serious.
심각하게 들려요
Uh, catastrophic forgetting, if you hear that, is saying that, um, if you take a pre-trained model
치명적인 망각이란 미리 훈련된 라마 3 같은
like llama 3.1 and you fine tune it with a large amount of data, it will get better and better at solving
모델을 말하는 거예요 Get 1 많은 양의 데이터로 미세 조정하면 여러분의 문제 해결에
your particular problem, but over time it will.
점점 더 나아집니다 시간이 지나면 그렇게 되죠
Over over training time it will start to forget some of the base information in the base model, and
훈련 시간이 지나면서 기본 모델의 기본 정보를 잊기 시작할 겁니다 그 결과 품질의 일부가
as a result, some of its quality might degrade if it's taken outside the specific kinds of questions
떨어질 수 있어요 여러분이 훈련하는 특정 종류의 질문을 벗어나면요
Um, and so that's a that's a behavior that's been noticed and that has, has some, some concerning
그런 행동이 눈에 띄었고 우려스러운 결과도 있었어요
So if you need to make sure that you don't lose any of the information in the base model, if that will
기본 모델에서 어떤 정보도 잃지 않도록 해야만 한다면 그게 여러분의 성능에 영향을
affect your performance, then you need to be careful about this.
미친다면 이걸 조심해야 해요
All right.
좋아요
So just to wrap up these then let me finish by saying that, uh, the the times when you typically use
마무리로 이 말만 할게요 보통 프롬프트할 때 프롬프트를 사용하는 시간은
them with prompting, it's often used as the starting point for a project.
프로젝트의 시작점으로 자주 사용돼요
Often your first version of your model will be perhaps a frontier model, and you will use prompting
종종 첫 번째 모델은 프런티어 모델일 수 있습니다. 프롬프트
as a way to, to add, uh, performance Rag is in the specific case where you want, you need the accuracy.
기능을 추가하는 방법으로 사용할 수도 있습니다. 퍼포먼스 래그는 정확성이 필요한 특정한 경우에 사용하죠.
You don't want to spend the extra money on training and you have an existing knowledge base of data.
훈련에 추가 비용을 쓰고 싶지 않고 이미 존재하는 데이터 기반도 갖고 싶지 않죠
Then.
그럼 말이죠
Then you're in perfectly suited for a Rag kind of workflow, and fine tuning is you have a specialized
그러면 래그 워크플로우에 완벽하게 적응하게 됩니다 미세 튜닝은 특별한 작업을 수행하는
task, you have a very high volume of data, and you need top performance.
것이고 데이터의 양이 매우 많기 때문에 최고의 성능이 필요하죠
Um, and, and you want nuance as well.
뉘앙스도 있어야 하고요
And that, of course, is a situation that we are in with our product price predictor.
물론 우리 제품 가격 예측기가 처한 상황이죠
We have tons of data.
데이터는 많아요
We have a specialized task.
특별한 작업이 있어요
We want top performance, and we do want a nuanced understanding of products so much that it can differentiate
우리는 최고의 성능을 원하고 제품에 대한 미묘한 이해도 원합니다 그래서 훌륭한
between a great variety in product prices.
제품 가격의 차이를 만들 수 있어야 하죠
Okay, I will pause here for one moment, and we will come back to wrap up the strategy section before
여기서 잠시 멈추고 전략 섹션을 마무리하러 돌아오겠습니다 그 후에
we then turn back to our data and get to curation.
데이터로 돌아가 큐레이션으로 가죠